I was still there. I really believe cinema teaches us to see. The way we show the world is going to change the way we see this world, and we live in a moment where the mass media are doing a terrible, terrible job at representing the world: violence, extremists, only spectacular events, only simplifications of everyday life. I think we are recording to regain a certain complexity. To reinvent life today, we have to make new forms of images. And it's very simple. Muito obrigado. (Applause) Bruno Giussani: Vincent, Vincent, Vincent. Merci. We have to prepare for the following performance, and I have a question for you, and the question is this: You show up in places like the ones you just have shown us, and you are carrying a camera and I assume that you are welcome but you are not always absolutely welcome.
Yo todavía estaba allí. Realmente creo que el cine nos enseña a ver. La forma de mostrar el mundo va a cambiar la forma que vemos este mundo y vivimos en un momento en el que los medios masivos están haciendo un trabajo terrible al representar el mundo: violencia, extremistas, solo eventos espectaculares, solo simplificaciones de la vida cotidiana. Creo que estamos grabando para recuperar una cierta complejidad. Para reinventar la vida de hoy, tenemos que hacer nuevas formas de imágenes. Y es muy simple. Muito obrigado. (Aplausos) Bruno Giussani: Vicente, Vicente, Vicente. Merci. Tenemos que prepararnos para la siguiente actuación, y quiero preguntarte algo y es lo siguiente: Te apareces en lugares como los que nos ha mostrado, y llevas una cámara y supongo que eres bienvenido pero seguro que no siempre eres totalmente bienvenido.
You walk into sacred rituals, private moments in a village, a town, a group of people. How do you break the barrier when you show up with a lens? VM: I think you break it with your body, more than with your knowledge. That's what it taught me to travel, to trust the memory of the body more than the memory of the brain. The respect is stepping forward, not stepping backward, and I really think that by engaging your body in the moment, in the ceremony, in the places, people welcome you and understand your energy. BG: You told me that most of the videos you have made are actually one single shot. You don't do much editing. I mean, you edited the ones for us at the beginning of the sessions because of the length, etc. Otherwise, you just go in and capture whatever happens in front of your eyes without much planning, and so is that the case? It's correct? VM: My idea is that I think that as long as we don't cut, in a way, as long as we let the viewer watch, more and more viewers are going to feel closer, are going to get closer to the moment, to that moment and to that place. I really think of that as a matter of respecting the viewer, to not cut all the time from one place to another, to just let the time go. BG: Tell me in a few words about your new project, "Híbridos," here in Brazil. Just before coming to TEDGlobal, you have actually been traveling around the country for that. Tell us a couple of things. VM: "Híbridos" is — I really believe Brazil, far from the cliches, is the greatest religious country in the world, the greatest country in terms of spirituality and in experimentations in spiritualities. And it's a big project I'm doing over this year, which is researching in very different regions of Brazil, in very different forms of cults, and trying to understand how people live together with spirituality nowadays. BG: The man who is going to appear onstage momentarily, and Vincent's going to introduce him, is one of the subjects of one of his past videos. When did you do a video with him? VM: I guess four years ago, four years in my first travel. BG: So it was one of your first ones in Brazil. VM: It was amongst the first ones in Brazil, yeah. I shot the film in Recife, in the place where he is from. BG: So let's introduce him. Who are we waiting for? VM: I'll just make it very short. It's a very great honor for me to welcome onstage one of the greatest Brazilian musicians of all time. Please welcome Naná Vasconcelos. BG: Naná Vasconcelos! (Applause) (Music) Naná Vasconcelos: Let's go to the jungle. (Applause)
Entras en rituales sagrados, en momentos privados en un pueblo, una ciudad, en un grupo de personas. ¿Cómo rompes la barrera cuando te presentas con una cámara? VM: Creo que la rompes con tu cuerpo, más que con el conocimiento. Eso es lo que me enseñó viajar, a confiar en la memoria del cuerpo más que en la memoria del cerebro. El respeto es un paso adelante, no ir hacia atrás, y realmente creo que mediante la participación del cuerpo en el momento, en la ceremonia, en los lugares, las personas te dan la bienvenida y entienden tu energía. BG: Me dijiste que la mayoría de los vídeos que haces son en realidad de una sola toma. Que no haces mucha edición. Es decir, las editaste para nosotros al inicio de las sesiones por su longitud, etc. De otra manera, solo tienes que entrar y filmar lo que pase ante tus ojos sin mucha planificación, ¿es así? ¿Es correcto? VM: Mi idea es que mientras no cortemos, de una manera, siempre y cuando dejamos que el espectador lo vea, más y más espectadores se van a sentir más cerca, van a estar más cerca del momento, para ese momento y ese lugar. Realmente creo que es una forma de respetar al espectador, no cortar todo el tiempo de un lugar a otro, y dejar que el tiempo pase. BG: Dime en pocas palabras algo de tu nuevo proyecto, "Híbridos", aquí en Brasil. Justo antes de venir a TEDGlobal, tú en realidad estuviste viajando por todo el país para eso. Cuéntanos un par de cosas. VM: "Híbridos" es... realmente creo que Brasil, lejos de los clichés, es el país religioso más grande del mundo, el país más grande en términos de espiritualidad y en experimentos espirituales. Y es un gran proyecto que estoy haciendo este año, en que estoy investigando en diferentes regiones de Brasil, en muy diferentes formas de cultos, y tratando de entender cómo la gente vive junto con la espiritualidad hoy en día. BG: El hombre que va a aparecer en el escenario en un momento, y Vincent lo va a presentar, es uno de los temas de uno de sus vídeos anteriores. ¿Cuándo hiciste un video con él? VM: Creo que hace cuatro años, cuatro años en mi primer viaje. BG: Así que fue uno de los primeros en Brasil. VM: Fue de los primeros en Brasil, sí. Realicé la película en Recife, en el lugar de dónde es. BG: Así que vamos a presentarle. ¿A quién estamos esperando? VM: Lo haré muy corto. Es un gran honor dar la bienvenida en el escenario a uno de los más grandes músicos brasileños de todos los tiempos. Démosle la bienvenida a Naná Vasconcelos. BG: ¡Naná Vasconcelos! (Aplausos) (Música) Naná Vasconcelos: Vayamos a la selva. (Aplausos)